Guide to the Southwestern Washington Research Unit Records 1943-1975
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Southwestern Washington Research Unit Records
1943-1975
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 72
5.5 linear feet of shelf space 6 boxes
This collection contains the records of the Southwestern Washington Research Unit.
The Southwestern Washington Research Unit, located in Vancouver, Washington, is an agricultural experiment station which operates under the auspices of Washington State University's College of Agriculture. The Research Unit is situated on the site of the former Clark County Poor Farm in northern Vancouver. Experimentation and research were begun in October, 1943; but it was not until early 1949 that the University gained control of the full 80 acres.
The station conducts research in commercial vegetables and fruit crops, insect and disease control, fertilizer development, irrigation, animal science, soils, seeds, and a variety of horticultural areas. Clark County is located at the northern end of the Willamette Valley, and it is roughly half urban and half rural. Vancouver, the county seat, is a fruit and vegetable processing center.
This collection contains the records of the Southwestern Washington Research Unit covering the years 1943-1975. Includes correspondence, reports, memos, etc., related to both government and the private sector. Information on crop experiments, technological developments, etc., from agricultural and industrial resources. Series III contains the personal files of D. F. Allmendinger, Perry Crandall (both were Research Unit Superintendents) and Glenn Wolfe, an experiment aide.
The records at the Southwestern Washington Research Unit are arranged in six distinct series. The first series, Correspondence, 1950-1968, is comprised of both incoming and outgoing general correspondence. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically, by incoming correspondent (the correspondent may be a person, business or institution), This group of letters and documents concerns a wide variety of University correspondence, professional correspondence, and information from agricultural and industrial sources. The second series, Subject File, 1943-1959, contains reports, memoranda, data, and other correspondence with related agencies in both government and the private sector. That series is arranged alphabetically by subject and covers the years 1943-1959, but bulks largest in the early 1950s. Series 3, Staff Correspondence Files, 1965-1975, contains the personal files of D. F. Allmendinger and Perry Crandall (both Research Unit Superintendents), and Glenn Wolf, an experiment aide. These files were labeled as such in the original accession and contain correspondence to various colleagues. Series 4, Project Reports, 1943-1964, is a collection of project reports and evaluations. Included in this series is information on crop experiments, technological developments (such as the mechanical bean pole harvester), and programs conducted by the research unit. Series 5, Photographs, is a collection of photographs and negatives depicting various scenes around the research unit, scientific data, and research project results. These photographs are generally not dated. The final series, 6, is an oversized ledger containing information pertaining to blackberry and strawberry research, growth records, and other data. It is dated 1946-1967.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The records of the Southwestern Washington Research Unit were transferred to the University Archives, Washington State University, in February, 1979 (UA 79-05).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University -- College of Agriculture -- Southwestern Washington Research Unit -- Records and correspondence.
Agricultural experiment stations-- Washington (State) -- Archives.; Agriculture -- Research -- Archives.; Agriculture -- Washington (State) -- Experimentation -- Archives.
Agriculture.; Washington (State).
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1950-1968
  - A-Z, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1-23, Items 250 items)
  - A-Y, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24-27, Items 250 items)
  - A-Z, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 28-30, Items 350 items)
  - A-Q, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 31-34, Items 350 items)
  - R-Z, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 35, Items 40 items)
  - A-Z, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 36-38, Items 300 items)
  - A-Z, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 39-40, Items 250 items)
  - A-Z, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 41-48, Items 600 items)
  - A-L, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 49-51, Items 250 items)
  - M-Z, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 52-54, Items 150 items)
  - A-Z, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 55-60, Items 350 items)
  - A-Z, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 61-64, Items 400 items)
  - A-Z, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 65-66, Items 150 items)
  - A-O, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 67-69, Items 250 items)
  - P-Z, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 70, Items 100 items)
  - A-Z, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 71-74, Items 400 items)
  - A-Z, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 75-77, Items 350 items)
  - A-Z, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 78-80, Items 250 items)
- Series 2: Subject File, 1943-1959
  - Abruzzi Foundation, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 81, Items 35 items)
  - Advisory Board-Station, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 82, Items 10 items)
  - Budget, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 83, Items 10 items)
  - Correspondence: Mt. Vernon, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 84, Items 10 items)
  - Correspondence: Puyallup, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 85, Items 15 items)
  - Correspondence: Unspecified, 1952-1957 (Box 4, Folder 86, Items 75 items)
  - County Agent, Clark, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 87, Items 50 items)
  - Cowlitz County, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 88, Items 40 items)
  - Crop and Soil Recommendation, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 89, Items 10 items)
  - Fertility Committee-Statewide, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 90, Items 15 items)
  - Flat Pea, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 91, Items 5 items)
  - Fluorine Prospects, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 92, Items 10 items)
  - Forage Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 93, Items 100 items)
  - Forestry and Range, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 94, Items 5 items)
  - Infiltration Data; 1954 (Box 4, Folder 95, Items 15 items)
  - Irrigation Data, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 96, Items 60 items)
  - Lime, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 97, Items 10 items)
  - Leaflets, 1951-1955 (Box 4, Folder 98, Items 50 items)
  - Midwest Barley Improvement, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 99, Items 50 items)
  - New Bulletin Lists, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 100, Items 75 items)
  - Projects, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 101, Items 15 items)
  - Organizational Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Box 5, Folder 102, Items 35 items)
  - Outlying Testing Program, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 103, Items 25 items)
  - Planting Data Calculation, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 104, Items 5 items)
  - Project Reports, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 105, Items 35 items)
  - Publications Procedures, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 106, Items 25 items)
  - Publicity, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 107, Items 25 items)
  - Red Russian Wheat, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 108, Items 15 items)
  - Severe's Pasture Plots, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 109, Items 10 items)
  - Silage, 1943, 1951-1955 (Box 5, Folder 110, Items 5 items)
  - Soil Moisture, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 111, Items 5 items)
  - Soil Sampling, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 112, Items 75 items)
  - Soil Test Results, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 113, Items 25 items)
  - Speech, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 114, Items 10 items)
  - Thompson's Seeder, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 115, Items 5 items)
  - Turf and Lawn, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 116, Items 10 items)
  - Weeds, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 117, Items 5 items)
- Series 3: Staff Correspondence Files, 1965-1975
  - Allmendinger, D. F., 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 118, Items 35 items)
  - Crandall, Perry, 1965-1967, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 119-122, Items 400 items)
  - Wolf, Glenn, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 123, Items 35 items)
- Series 4: Project Reports, 1943-1964
  - Barley Varieties, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 124, Items 10 items)
  - Bean Data, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 125, Items 5 items)
  - Field Day Programs, 1948-1964 (Box 5, Folder 126, Items 20 items)
  - Horticulture Reports, 1943, 1950-51 (Box 5, Folder 127, Items 15 items)
  - Mechanical Pole Bean Harvester Data, 1956-1962 (Box 5, Folder 128, Items 35 items)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1949-1959 (Box 5, Folder 129, Items 50 items)
  - Pole Bean Harvester Data, 1959, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 130, Items 10 items)
  - Washington Irrigation, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 131, Items 15 items)
  - Winter Injury Report, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 132, Items 5 items)
- Series 5: Photographs, n.d.
  - Cherries under microscope, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133, Items 100 items)
  - Chromosomes, negatives and data, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 134, Items 100 items)
  - Facility and personnel, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 135, Items 100 items)
  - Negatives, microphotography, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 136, Items 100 items)
  - Negatives, photographic research, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 137, Items 100 items)
  - Prints, photographic research, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 138, Items 75 items)
  - Christmas trees, prints and negatives, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 139, Items 100 items)
- Series 6: Data Ledger, 1946-1967
  - Data concerning projects and experiments, 1946-1967 (Box o.s.)